A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, McCloy Committee Transcripts FA1620
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, McCloy Committee Transcripts
1962 March-April
Rockefeller Archive Center
McCloy, John J. (John Jay), 1895-1989
Ford Foundation
FA1620
1.1 Cubic Feet 3 letter document containers
Biographical / Historical
At its September 1961 meeting, the Ford Foundation's Board of Trustees "RESOLVED that the Chairman appoint a committee of Trustees and officers to review the programs of the Foundation and report to the Board on program areas which might be newly entered into and programs, if any, which might be discontinued." At the meeting of the Executive Committee of the Board in October, "The Chairman reported on the composition ofthe Committee on Objectives of the Foundation...." Joseph Slater, who had rejoined the Foundation staff at the behest of John J. McCloy to serve as the Study Director of the Committee, acted as rapporteur at the first meeting ofthe Committee which was held on October 26 after the Board's Executive Committee adjourned.
The Committee undertook to review the Foundation's "policies, programs, and operations...and to recommend policies, programs, and operations for the 1960s...." Those appointed to serve on the Special Committee were: John J. McCloy, Chairman of the Board of Trustees (and Chair of the Committee); Donald K. David, Vice Chairman of the Board of Trustees; and Henry T. Heald, President of the Foundation. Other members of the Committee were John Cowles, McNeil Lowry, Julius A. Stratton, Bethuel M. Webster, Milton Katz, Dyke Brown, Clarence H. Faust, F. F. Hill, William McPeak, James M. Nicely, Joseph M. McDaniel, and Joseph E. Slater.
The Committee was ostensibly formed as a ten year review committee, but was also implicitly intended to address proper relationships between Board, President and staff. The Committee assembled staff appraisals of the programs of the Foundation in the previous decade and conducted extensive surveys both inside and outside the Foundation to determine courses of action for the future.
The names 'Special Committee on Program Review' and 'Survey Committee' were used interchangeably. Individual sessions held between March and April 1962 focused on different program areas including Education, Economics, International Relations, Science and Technology, and the Arts.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series: Session Transcripts
Other Finding Aids
For more background information and other copies of the McCloy Committee proceedings, see FA708 Ford Foundation records, Records of the Special Committee for Program Policy Review in the 1960s, 1952-1963.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2019:106 (Box 42467).
Scope and Contents
The collection includes transcripts of 12 sessions of the Proceedings of the Survey Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation (also known as the McCloy Committee or the Special Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation). Individual sessions focused on potential program goals in Education, Economics, International Relations, Science and Technology, and the Arts.
Arts; Economics; Education; International relations; Science; Technology; Ford Foundation
- Session Transcripts, 1
  - Proceedings of the Special Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Original - Session I: Education; Session II: Economics, 1962 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Proceedings of the Special Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Master Set - Session I: Education; Session II: Economics, 1962 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Proceedings of the Special Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Original - Session III: International Relations; Session IV: Less Developed Countries, 1962 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Proceedings of the Special Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Master Copy - Session III: International Relations; Session IV: Less Developed Countries, 1962 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Proceedings of the Survey Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Sessions V and VI, 1962 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Discussion of area planning, urban development and renewal, public administration, transportation, highways and bridges, airports and ports, rapid transit, educational cultural, industrial integration, health, and design
  - Proceedings of the Survey Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Sessions VII and VIII, 1962 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Proceedings of the Survey Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Original - Sessions VII and VIII, 1962 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Proceedings of the Special Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Original - Sessions IX and X, 1962 April 13 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Proceedings of the Survey Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Original - Sessions XI and XII, 1962 April 14 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Proceedings of the Survey Committee on Program Review of the Ford Foundation - Sessions XI and XII, 1962 April 14 (Box 3, Folder 10)